[Music]
if you look at the classics the most
frequently cited articles in the
scientific nutrition literature the
original glycemic index paper comes out
in number 10 cited more than a thousand
times and learning about fruit
vegetables and cancer prevention was a
hallmark but hitting the top five cited
more than 2 000 times
dietary modulation of the human
microbiome introducing the concept
of prebiotics prebiotics are the food
components that feed and nourish the
good bacteria in our gut like fiber and
resistant starch in general eating high
fiber plant foods is a good foundation
for a prebiotic rich diet
once upon a time fiber was just thought
of as just the undigested component of
foods known only for bulking up stools
and keeping our bowels regular
then we discovered an array of receptors
in the body in which fiber breakdown
products fit in like a lock and key
we feed our good bacteria with fiber and
they feed us right back munching the
fiber and creating short chain fatty
acids that get absorbed into our
bloodstream and fit into these receptors
that are expressed on immune cells and
generally mediate a direct
anti-inflammatory effect so the reason
for lower systemic inflammation in
plant-based eaters may not just be due
to the abundance of anti-inflammatory
molecules in plant foods or the
avoidance of pro-inflammatory molecules
in animal foods but from the production
of anti-inflammatory molecules from
scratch by our good gut bugs when we
feed them fiber
just to give you an idea how protective
fiber-rich foods can be those randomized
to get advice to eat fiber-rich plant
foods during radiation therapy for
cancer didn't just experience reduced
toxicity during the treatments but even
a full year later
indeed the benefits of fiber are
supported by more than a century of
research prospective studies show
striking reductions in death from all
causes put together including total
cancer deaths total cardiovascular
disease deaths and incidents stroke
incidence and incidence of colorectal
breast and esophageal cancer and
dose-response relationships suggest that
the more the better in terms of
protecting against heart attacks and
stroke type 2 diabetes and cancer so at
a minimum
fiber intake should be no less than 25
to 29 grams per day with additional
benefits likely to crew with higher
intakes yet the average american only
consumes about 16 grams of fiber per day
we have co-evolved over millennia with
gut bacteria to the point of reliance on
our good gut bugs a kind of symbiosis
for fiber digestion and the production
of short chain fatty acids and even
certain vitamins yet we're not holding
up our end of the bargain we're supposed
to be providing up to 100 or so grams of
fiber a day and we are barely passing
along a measly 16 grams the simplest
solution the simplest approach to remedy
this lack of dietary fiber is to
encourage consumption of whole food
plant-based nutrition
[Music]
you